{
  "title": "Engineering_Mathematics - Engineering_Mathematics — Slot 6 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Engineering_Mathematics — Slot 6",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>With respect to the numerical evaluation of the definite integral,\\(K=\\int_{a}^{b}x^{2}dx\\) , where a and b are given, which of the following statements is/are TRUE? <br>\n(I) The value of K obtained using the trapezoidal rule is always greater than or equal to the\nexact value of the definite integral. <br>\n(II) The value of K obtained using the Simpson's rule is always equal to the exact value of\nthe definite integral. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I only</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>II only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Both I and II</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Neither I nor II</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Both I and II</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2080/gate2014-3-46#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>Let A be a square matrix size n x n. Consider the following pseudocode. What is the\nexpected output?<pre><code> C = 100;\nfor i = 1 to n do\n   for j = 1 to n do\n   {\n      Temp = A[ i ] [ j ] + C ;\n      A [ i ] [ j ] = A [ j ] [ i ] ;\n      A [ j ] [ i ] = Temp - C ;\n   }\nfor i = 1 to n do\n    for j = 1 to n do\n         output (A[ i ] [ j ]); </code></pre> <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>The matrix A itself</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Transpose of the matrix A</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Adding 100 to the upper diagonal elements and subtracting 100 from lower diagonal elements of A</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of these</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>The matrix A itself</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2044/gate2014-3-10#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>If \\(\\int_{0}^{2\\pi}|x sinx| dx=k \\pi\\), then the value of k is equal to _______. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "4",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2040/gate2014-3-6#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>If V1 and V2 are 4-dimensional subspaces of a 6-dimensional vector space V, then the smallest possible dimension of  V1\\(\\cap\\)V2 is _______. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "2",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2039/gate2014-3-5#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>Which one of the following statements is TRUE about every n x n matrix with only real\neigenvalues? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>If the trace of the matrix is positive and the determinant of the matrix is negative, at least one of its eigenvalues is negative.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>If the trace of the matrix is positive, all its eigenvalues are positive.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>If the determinant of the matrix is positive, all its eigenvalues are positive.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>If the product of the trace and determinant of the matrix is positive, all its eigenvalues are positive.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>If the trace of the matrix is positive and the determinant of the matrix is negative, at least one of its eigenvalues is negative.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2038/gate2014-3-4#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>The product of the non-zero eigenvalues of the matrix <br>\\(\\begin{bmatrix} 1 &amp; 0&amp;0 &amp; 0&amp;1 \\\\ 0&amp; 1&amp; 1 &amp; 1 &amp; 0\\\\ 0&amp; 1&amp; 1&amp; 1&amp;0 \\\\ 0 &amp; 1 &amp; 1 &amp; 1 &amp; 0\\\\ 1&amp;0 &amp; 0&amp;0 &amp; 1 \\end{bmatrix}\\) <br> is_______. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "6",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2013/gate2014-2-47#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>In the Newton-Raphson method, an initial guess of \\(x_{0}=2\\) is made and the sequence\n\\(x_{0},x_{1},x_{2}...\\) is obtained for the function <br> \\(0.75x^{3}-2x^{2}-2x+4=0\\)<br> Consider the statements <br>\n(I) \\(x_{3}\\)=0. <br>\n(II) The method converges to a solution in a finite number of iterations. <br>\nWhich of the following is TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Only I</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Only II</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Both I and II</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Neither I nor II</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Only I</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2012/gate2014-2-46#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>A non-zero polynomial f(x) of degree 3 has roots at x = 1,x = 2 and x = 3. Which one of the following must be TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(f(0)f(4) \\lt 0\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(f(0)f(4) \\gt 0\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(f(0)+f(4) \\gt 0\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(f(0)+f(4) \\lt 0\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(f(0)f(4) \\lt 0\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1957/gate2014-2-5#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>If the matrix A is such that  <br>\\(\\begin{bmatrix} 2\\\\ -4\\\\ 7 \\end{bmatrix}\\begin{bmatrix} 1 &amp;9 &amp;5 \\end{bmatrix}\\) <br> Then the determinant of A is equal to ________. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "0",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1956/gate2014-2-4#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>A function f(x) is continuous in the interval [0,2]. It is known that f(0)=f(2)=-1 and f(1)=1.\nWhich one of the following statements must be true? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>There exists a y in the interval (0,1) such that f(y)=f(y+1)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>For every y in the interval (0,1), f(y)=f(2-y)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>The maximum value of the function in the interval (0.2) is 1</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>There exists a y in the interval (0,1) such that f(y)=-f(2-y)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>There exists a y in the interval (0,1) such that f(y)=f(y+1)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1925/gate2014-1-47#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>The function \\(f(x)=x sin x\\) satisfies the following equation: \\(f''(x)+f(x)+tcos x=0\\). The value of t is______. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "-2",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1924/gate2014-1-46#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>Let the function <br> \\(f(\\theta)=\\begin{vmatrix} sin\\theta &amp; cos\\theta &amp; tan\\theta \\\\ sin(\\frac{\\pi}{6}) &amp; cos(\\frac{\\pi}{6}) &amp; tan(\\frac{\\pi}{6})\\\\ sin(\\frac{\\pi}{3})&amp; cos(\\frac{\\pi}{3}) &amp; tan(\\frac{\\pi}{3}) \\end{vmatrix}\\) <br>  where \\(\\theta \\in [\\frac{\\pi}{6},\\frac{\\pi}{3}]\\) and \\(f'(\\theta )\\) denote the derivative of  f with respect to \\(\\theta\\) . Which of the following\nstatements is/are TRUE? <br>(I) There existrs \\(\\theta \\in (\\frac{\\pi}{6},\\frac{\\pi}{3})\\) such that \\(f'(\\theta )=0\\) <br> (I) There existrs \\(\\theta \\in (\\frac{\\pi}{6},\\frac{\\pi}{3})\\) such that \\(f'(\\theta )\\neq 0\\) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I only</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>II only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Both I and II</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Neither I nor II</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Both I and II</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1763/gate2014-1-6#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>The value of the dot product of the eigenvectors corresponding to any pair of different eigenvalues of a 4-by-4 symmetric positive definite matrix is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "0",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1760/gate2014-1-5#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following system of equations: <br>     3x + 2y = 1 <br>\n4x + 7z = 1 <br>\nx + y + z = 3 <br>\nx - 2y + 7z = 0 <br>\nThe number of solutions for this system is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "1",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1757/gate2014-1-4#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>What is the least value of the function \\(f(x) = 2x^{2}-8x-3\\) in the interval [0, 5]? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2013)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>-15</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>7</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>-11</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>-3</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>-11</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/44161/isro-2013-49\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}